Guide to the West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records 2010.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Oral Histories, 28 Gigabytes in 288 files
  - Stanislaus, Lamuel, 1994 August 4; 2010.019.28
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Grenada; Grenadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Stanislaus, Lamuel, Dr.; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Thomas, Tricia, 1994 August 3; 2010.019.29
    Tricia Thomas was born in New York City. From age two until the age of six, she lived in Trinidad. Her family then returned to New York to live in Brooklyn. At the time of the interview she was sixteen years old and living in Edison, New Jersey. Many of her family members participated in Brooklyn's Carnival as masqueraders with Hawks International Mas Camp. Thomas was a member of the steel pan youth band, Caribbean American Sports & Cultural Youth Movement (CASYM), which required her to make multiple, weekly visits into Brooklyn for rehearsals and to commit to prolonged stays during the summer season before Carnival.
    In this interview Tricia Thomas discusses her participation in Brooklyn's Carnival and in playing mas, the themed costume participation, from the age of three. She reflects on her choice to play the steel pan rather than mas and describes her family's participation in Carnival. A participant or observer of Carnival in a number of cities, she provides her opinion on the differences in the Carnivals and notes the pros and cons of the each. Noting the lack of media recognition of the Carnival, Thomas sees a need for the New York population to acknowledge and respect the Caribbean community's desire to preserve the cultural meaning of Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Toronto (Ont.); Trinidad; Thomas, Tricia; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Thompson, Jay, 1994 October 5; 2010.019.30
    Jay Thompson was born in on the island of St. Kitts. She moved to New York as a teenager, where she lived from the age of fourteen to seventeen. She then returned to St. Kitts. After finishing school and working for the government of St. Kitts, Thompson returned to New York City at the age of twenty-three. In 1994, when the interview occurred, Thompson resided in the Bronx with her two children.
    In this interview, Jay Thompson discusses her immigration to New York City, her family, and her experience as a food vendor at Brooklyn's West Indian American Day Carnival. She notes that her booth is a central meeting place for St. Kittitians. Thompson also relates that the booth did not operate during the 1994 Carnival because of cost and time constraints imposed on the Carnival that year; a product of a conflict with the Hasidic Jewish community's celebration of Rosh Hashanah. She also discusses the St. Kitts Carnival, which occurs between Christmas and New Year's. Interview conducted by Maureen Mahon.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Saint Kitts and Nevis; Street vendors |z New York (State) |z New York; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Thompson, Jay; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Toney, Joyce, 1994 September 19; 2010.019.31
    Joyce Toney was born in St. Vincent & the Grenadines. She immigrated to the United States to attend college and moved to Brooklyn in 1972. At the time of this interview in 1994, Joyce Toney was a professor in the Department of Africana & Puerto Rican/Latino Studies at the City University of New York, Hunter College. Professor Toney sat as chairperson of that department from 1998-2002 and the as director of the Women Studies program at the same college from 2002-2005.
    In this interview, Joyce Toney discusses her participation in the carnivals in Brooklyn, Toronto and St. Vincent, noting the differences between the events. She also considers how the structure of the carnivals in Toronto and St. Vincent could alleviate the difficulties of the West Indian American Day Carnival in Brooklyn, New York. Toney reminisces about starting a "band," a musical group of mas players (the costumed participants of Carnival), in the 1970s. She discusses the definition of carnival, describing the process of playing mas. Toney discusses the camaraderie between mas players, noting that togetherness in mas does not necessarily signify a unified Caribbean community. She discusses the politicization of Carnival and the possibilities of using the popularity of Carnival to further the needs of the Caribbean community. The interview ends in a discussion of Carnival as an expression of Caribbean identity. Interview conducted by Maureen Mahon.
    Barbados; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; Toronto (Ont.); Trinidad; Toney, Joyce; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Weeks, Daphne, 1994 May 6; 2010.019.32
    Daphne Weeks was born in Port of Spain, Trinidad. References made within the interview indicate she may have been in her late seventies or early eighties in 1994. From a middle class family, she was a prolific musician who became a big band musician during the post-World War II era. With her band, Daphne Weeks and Her Versatile Caribbean Band, Weeks performed in the Harlem West Indian American parade and masquerade balls. She also participated in the Brooklyn West Indian American Day Carnival for twenty-six years. Daphne Weeks died on October 8, 2004.
    In this interview, Daphne Weeks describes her musical career in Trinidad and her immigration to the United States in 1947. Settling in Brooklyn, she played jazz and calypso in the big band clubs of Harlem. During her early career, Weeks encountered Count Basie, Duke Ellington, and Billie Holiday. She also reflects on many of the West Indian American musicians of the period: Don Wilson, Lankey Belasco, Ohaldo Williams and Willie Gayle. Weeks discusses her participation in the earlier West Indian parade in Harlem; relating her experiences with the founder Jessie Wattle and Wattle's successor Evans Butcher. She tells of the event that may have ended the parades in Harlem and remembers the meeting between Rufus Gorin and Carlos Lezama that initiated the Brooklyn Carnival. She also defines and discusses the Dame Lorraine dances that once concluded the Carnival parades. Weeks discusses her twenty-six year participation in the Brooklyn West Indian American Day Carnival, noting the changes in the parade. She reflects on the police's relationship to the Carnival community, providing her opinion of what causes conflict between the parade spectators and the police. The interview ends with Daphne Weeks returning to a discussion of her musical career. Interview conducted by Bill Pincheon.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Trinidadians |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Trinidad; Lezama, Carlos; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Windsor, Gailene, 1995 April 19; 2010.019.33
    Gailene Windsor was born in St. Vincent & the Grenadines. She moved to Brooklyn, New York in 1979. When she was interviewed in 1995, Windsor was very active in the Vincentian community abroad, acting as the general secretary of a Vincentian-based New York Carnival organization. She played mas (masquerade) in St. Vincent and in the West Indian American Day Carnival, Brooklyn. In 2016, Windsor was a member of the non-governmental organization, The St. Vincent & Grenadines Diaspora Committee of New York.
    The interview begins with Gailene Windsor's consideration of the political reasons why the Carnival in St. Vincent has declined in the years preceding 1995 and how the island's economy will be affected by the lack of Vincentian diaspora in the event. She discusses her involvement in promoting the culture of Vincentian community and her participation in the Brooklyn-based West Indian American Day Carnival. Windsor notes the lack of media coverage the Carnival receives and suggests political and community solutions. She addresses the cultural conflicts between the Hasidic Jewish and West Indian communities of Crown Heights, suggesting solutions to ease the tension. She also discusses the need for planning and financial support from the local government for the parade, noting the need for the Caribbean community to unify its population in order to gain political clout. Windsor addresses the emergence of technological advancements in Carnival mas costumes and music, noting the loss of steel pan music to soca, calypso and reggae. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Multiculturalism; Race identity; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Windsor, Gailene
- Series 2: Oral History Transcripts
  - Adams, Val, 1994 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adolphus, Jeffrey, 1994 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alexander, Jean, 1994 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alexander, Kendell, 1994 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brewster, Randy, 1994 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brewster, Winston, 1995 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Byron, Cheryl, 1994 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cadogan, Glenda, 1995 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clavery, Francis "Jackie", 1994 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cowie, Sylvia and Jamilla, 1994 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - DaSilva, Dwight, 1994 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Davis, Kelvin "Fuzzy", 1994 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Davis, Paula, 1994 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dublin, Angela, 1995 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Evelyn, Terry, 1994 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gilbert, Elimus, 1995 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lezama, Carlos, 1994 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pope, Kelvin "Duke", 1995 January 28 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Quamina, Joyce, 1994 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Quamina, Joyce, 1994 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reid, Michelle Quamina, 1994 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Remy, Kwame, 1995 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rennie, Yvette, 1994 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Roberts, Michael, 1994 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Seddio, Frank, 1994 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Simpson, Charles, 1994 September 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Smith, Frank, 1994 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stanislaus, Dr. Lamuel, 1994 August 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Summaries, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Thomas, Tricia, 1994 August 3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Thompson, Jay, 1994 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Toney, Joyce, 1994 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Weeks, Dapne, 1994 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Windsor, Gailene, 1995 April 19 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cassettes, 1994-1995 (Box 3-4)
- Series 3: Photographs
  This series includes: contact sheets; negatives from photographers H. Roger Celestin, Paul Lewis and Kristen Elmquist; 8 1/2 x 11 color prints by H. Roger Celestin; and 4 x 5 color prints by Dwan Reece King, Kristin Elmquist, Paul Lewis and H. Roger Celestin. Detailed explanations of the photographers and numbering of this series is located in the "Photo Documentation and Description" folder in box 5. "Photo Interviews and Descriptions" in box 5 contains photographs interspersed with descriptions and biographical information on those pictured. The photographs depict parade events, band rehearsals, costume making and many of the narrators from the oral history interviews in series 1. The individuals pictured include: Randy Brewster, Jackie Clavery, Daphne Weeks, Fuzzy Davis, Frankie and Claudette Wall Kenneth Antoine, Jeffrey Adolphus, Joyce Quamina, Michelle Quamina, Carlos Lezma, Cheryl Byron and Michael Roberts. The prints also depict the following groups and bands: Aquarium Productions, The Promise, St. Vincent, Casym Boys, T&T Garage Boys, JuJu Warriors Mas Camp, Savage, Pan Rebels, Rage, Pauline and Associates, Marge and Associates, Caribbean People's Organization, Utica Boys, Sesame Flyers, Hawks Fantasy Warrors, Amazonia, W. Millington Mas Productions, and Devils.
  - Labor Day Carnival, #0001, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Casym Boys and Parents, #0002, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Roberts, Cheryl and Michael, #0003, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photo Documentation and Descriptions, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Negatives, Paul Lewis, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lt. Stitchie, Ju-Ju Warriorrs Camp, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Saint Vincent, Casym Boys, T & T Garage Boys, Raphael and Friends, Aquarium, #5379, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Aquarium, The Prommise, #5378, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Crowds, Floats, Kiddie's Carnival, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Promise, Casym Boys, Pan Rebels, #5381, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Antoine, Kenneth, Jeffrey Adolphus, Carib News, Saint Vincent, #5377, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Caribbean People's Organization, Utica Boys, #5376, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pauline and Associates, Rage, Saint Vincent, Marge and Associates, #5348, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Quamina, Joyce, Culture of Black Creation, Savage, #5388, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Character of Bands and Reggae Night, #5363, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Contact Sheets, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photo Interviews (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Labor Day Carnival, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Brewster, Randy and Jackie Clavery, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kiddie's Carnival, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Large Prints, #8323, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pan Rebels and Charlie's, 1995 July (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Negatives, Kiddie's Carnival, #9324, 1995 September 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Negatives, Pan Rebels, Charlie's, #7116, 1995 July (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Negatives, W. Millington and F. and C. Wall, #9088, 1995 August (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, Daphne Weeks, Fuzzy Davis and Pan Rebels, 1995 July (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Negatives, Randy Brewster and Jackie Clavery, #8865, 1995 June 27 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Negatives, Labor Day Carnival, #9357, 1995 September 4 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series 4: Research Materials
  - Articles, 1992-1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bands and Band Leaders, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bibliographies, 1989-1990s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Brewster, Randy Materials, 1984-1995 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Calypso/Steelband References, circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Caribbean Community Issues, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Caribbean Festival Arts, Saint Louis Art Museum, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Caribbean Stores in Brooklyn, circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Carnivals in Other Cities, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Contacts, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Distribution Materials, 1980-1981, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Everybody's Caribbean American Magazine, 1990, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Everybody's Carribean American Magazine, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Exhibit Objects (Potential), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - General, 1980s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - General, 1987-1994, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Grants, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Guide to Resources, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Hill, Donald R. "A History of West Indian Carnival in New York City to 1978", 1993 January (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Liverpool, Hollis Urban "Rituals of Power and Rebellion: the Carnival Tradition in Trinidad and Tobago", 1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1990s (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Notting Hill Carnival, 1980-1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Schomburg Center Photos (copies), undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Trinidad Carnival, 1970s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Carib Beat: The Entertainment Magazine, 1994 June-July (Box 9, Item 1-2)
  - The New York Carib News, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Item 3-10)
  - New York Newsday Clipping, 1994 September 16 (Box 9, Item 11)
  - New York Times Metro Section, 1995 February (Box 9, Item 12)
  - Village Voice, 1994 September 6 (Box 9, Item 13)